hi there um just before I get into the
content of this video I want to respond
to a couple of comments I've had on the
last one along the lines of you can
never really get rid of rival richness
there's always going to be things which
are scarce
rival versus is not only rooted in
scarcity this kind of thing and and I
agree with all of that I'm not taking
issue the point I was trying to make was
that rival richness has torn apart
civilizations in the past right and that
unless gain be can address the question
of rivalries dynamics in the society and
figure out a way of effectively
incentivizing non-rival brisant
anti-bible risk behavior then the
civilizational self-terminate for
exactly the same reasons that
civilizations in the past are terminated
and for the reasons that I've already
gone into so you know it's not uh wasn't
trying to suggest for a moment that it's
easy or that there's a readi solution
out there there anyone could just snap
their fingers and get rid of rivalries
dynamics I wasn't trying to suggest that
for a moment all I was trying to say
what is it if it is not addressed if a
solution is not found then it won't be
gained B it will simply be the next
iteration of game 8 now of course how we
go about doing that is another matter
and that's kind of what the subject of
the video this video today's video is
about the formation of decentralized
collective intelligence distributed
sense making networks which have the
capabilities to be way more effective
and responsive than the existing
top-down broadcast structures that we
have
so in this video I want to talk about
the difference between the broadcast
top-down modality of game A's decision
making and sense making processes versus
the opposite of that which is what my
game beat might look like so
decentralized distributed networks of
intelligence of sense making of decision
making and so as I said in the first
video the broadcast modality that exists
in game a and as always existed in game
a is basically a top-down thing so a few
people at the top have the right for
whatever reason to make decisions and to
evaluate information around and make
sense of what's going on the world make
decisions accordingly and then pass
those decisions down and everybody else
is expected to follow those and I mean
and this structure you know it's not
just the government or the Emperor or
the king or whatever at the top is that
that structure exists all the way down
and so you know you follows instructions
from people above you and you pass
instructions on to the people below you
and so on and so on and so on and and
you see microcosm that this structure
exists everywhere I mean I was a teacher
for nearly 20 years and the education
system the education system is exactly
like that you have one teacher standing
at the front of the really have rows of
children front the teacher imparts
knowledge the children absorb knowledge
you know it's it's broadcast the teacher
is broadcasting to their students and it
is the students job to tune into the
broadcast listen carefully and then be
able to repeat it and respond according
to the rules that they've been given and
to a degree this is fine I mean it works
right it's worked for a long time so you
know it's not entirely invalid it starts
to break down when the people handing
you and the people who are qualified to
speak and are telling everybody else
what to do are not doing so in good
faith or are not doing so in the light
of the best possible information and
things like that and until relatively
recently we as ordinary members of
society all we could do really was tune
into the TV or read the paper or would
ever receive the received wisdom and
that was reality right that was
journalism and television and school and
so on they made sense of the
world for us and we acted on that
information and acted accordingly now
however with the Internet we have access
at an individual level to a huge
plethora of information and this has
changed everything and so the old sense
making networks the news networks the
established newspapers this kind of
thing you know they're there people are
not listening to them anymore and for
very good reason because they have as
they've been losing market share in
order to try and keep hold of that
market share they become more and more
and more polarized more and more and
more outrageous and less and less sense
actually comes out of them and so people
have started looking elsewhere so this
decentralized sense-making has actually
already started I mean this is very much
in the process of happening this shift
away from big central information
distribution distribution networks to
you know small YouTube channels and
blogs and so on this is already well
underway if you think about it there's
broadcast modality we're only a few
people get to make sense of the world to
make decisions there's a shocking waste
of possibility right I mean there are
potentially millions of people who could
be contributing to a thought pool on any
particular idea or problem or whatever
it might be and so the decentralized
networks would be able to potentially
employ a far greater range of human
potential than the broadcast network
than the broadcast modality of a
possibly could Jordan Peterson has
likened this change in the media
landscape as nothing short of a
Gutenberg type revolution you know the
invention of the printing press and I
think he's absolutely right but it's
also very much in its infancy you know
nobody really knows yet what sort of
shape it's going to end up taking I
think I think it was Jordan Hall I'm
pretty sure I heard him referring to
it's kind of like an infant right you
know this new emerging intelligence this
new emerging collective intelligence is
like an infant you know he can't hold
his head up straight you can't focus
sighs I can't grab hold of anything bar
it's absolutely bursting with potential
and I think to some people at least
watching this video the fact that I
can't sort of just lay out this is how
these centralized networks are going to
be constructed and this is what they're
going to do and so on
I can't is lay them out in clear turns
is is is somewhat frustration but if I
may suggest this is a product of the
fact that we have been brought up to
respond to broadcast we want to be
presented with a ready-made solution and
be able to just act on those
instructions right rather than
contending with the idea that if the
important thing is to create the
sense-making apparatus that can come up
with the solutions and that until you
come up with the sense-making apparatus
and there is no you know the solutions
would emerge from that there's no
knowing what those solutions are going
to be because they're complex and this
is what the next video is going to be
about is the complex is it's complicated
but the solutions that will emerge from
these decentralized networks are going
to be complex in nature because they've
emerged from the interaction of
complexity so yeah nobody can see in in
advance what they're going to be and and
that can be a frustration but as I said
just a moment ago this is a product of
the fact that we've been brought up in a
broadcast environment and all we have
been trained to do is receive
instructions and act on them right and
so the decentralized networks require of
us as individuals that we are willing to
shoulder a certain degree of
responsibility for truthful
communication and earnest communication
and nonrival risk communication all
feeds into this and it also leads I'm
gonna make a whole separate video on
this because I think is I think it's
really really really important because
it actually tackles all three of the
things I'm talking about in this video
rival richness broadcast modality and
complexity it gets a hand on all three
of these things it's a really concrete
attainable protocol that everybody can
can start to practice namely rule Omega
and so the idea of rule Omega is that
everybody has valid perspective to
contribute to a particular problem you
know if they're interested in it and so
these collective intelligences will be
able to be far more responsive far more
creative than the exist
in static top-down institutional
structures that currently exist in game
a game B's sense making apparatus is
likely to consist of this emerging type
of intelligence where people all around
the world who are interested in a
particular area whatever it might be can
communicate with each other and refine
and own ideas
so given their much greater flexibility
and possibility for creativity these
decentralized distributed intelligence
networks could potentially come up with
solutions to how to for example
incentivize anti rivalries behavior in
society where as you know we're
solutions to things like this have
eluded us in the past this decentralized
modality as well affords the opportunity
to experiment on small scales you know
and if a new social construction or any
whatever you don't have to have roll it
out across the whole world all at once
right it can be it can be contained in
in one place and and when it goes wrong
the mess can be cleared up and and and
the damage limited so you know the whole
idea of one small group besides and
everybody has to do it you know this is
dangerous when bad decisions are made so
this decentralized thing also has the
huge advantage of allowing small-scale
experimentation to make sure things work
before they get rolled out and once
again just you know going back through
the collapse of civilizations in the
past corruption and rotting from within
of the institutional structures again
has been foundational to the collapse of
every single civilization that has gone
before and so once again if game B is to
be truly different and transformative
and enduring and resilient then it needs
to tackle this thing which has come up
again and again and again and again and
again namely that top-down broadcast
networks collapse under the weight of
their own bureaucracy and corruption in
the long run every time and so I think
that's about all I have to say in this
broadcast versus distributed networks
but in the fifth one of these I'm gonna
do an episode on all Omega which is all
about how those networks could actually
function okay thanks very much for
watching see you next time